Guide to the Naval History Society Records 1907-1943 (bulk 1909-1936) MS 439.53
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Correspondence (1909-1943)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Acknowledgments: Gurn's "Life of John Barry", 1934 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Col. and Mrs. Barnes with Miss Barck, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Office of Naval Records, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Acknowledgments: "Quasi War with France", 1936 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Letter to members, 1936 November 16 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1943 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Blank stationery: cards, letterhead, envelopes, bookplates, Undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Series III: Membership records (1910-1943)
  The membership records include lists of members in various categories (individual, life, honorary, resigned, died), signed cards noting acceptance or decline of membership, members' war service records, records of dues payments, and proxies for meetings; as well as newspaper clippings of members' obituaries. The mailing list for a proposed Marine Museum of the City of New York was probably used as a source of addresses for potential Naval History Society members. Also included is a guest book of signatures, perhaps kept at annual meetings. Additional information on membership can also be found in some of the Annual Reports (Subseries I. Administrative Records), which include lists of current members for the year; and in account books in Subseries V. Financial Records.
  Correspondence sent to all members was moved to Subseries II. Correspondence, and arranged there chronologically.
  - Membership lists, 1910, 1911, 1916, 1919-1923 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Membership acknowledgments, 1910-1919 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Membership lists, 1926-1936 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Biographical accounts of members of the Naval History Society: newspaper clippings, obituaries, 1928-1937 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Biographical accounts of members of the Naval History Society: newspaper clippings, obituaries, 1928-1937, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Mailing list: Marine Museum of the City of New York, 1931 April 1 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: newspaper obituaries of members, 1935-1943 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - List of members to receive volume "Quasi War with France", 1936 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Printed notices of nomination to Society, undated (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Stubs for dues; signed note on question of increasing dues; signed proxies for annual meetings; returned bills for dues paid; account of dues paid, 1915-1931 (Box 22)
  - Member cards; war service records, institutional members, life members, around 1917-1926 (Box 23)
  - Returned and paid notices, annual dues, 1929-1936 (Box 24)
  - Signatures [Guest book], 1916 June 10-1924 September 10 (Volume 2)
- Series IV: Library records (1907-1943)
  The library records include acquisitions lists, library catalog cards, publishers' catalogs, clippings regarding books of interest for possible acquisition, photographs of the installation of items from the collection at an unspecified location, various unorganized research notes in different hands on subjects including the Lloyd family of Long Island, and the library accession book. The latter documents acquisitions of both published books and manuscript materials, by date and donor, prices paid for items bought, as well as the library's classification system.
  Historical Note
  The Library was formed originally from the collection of John Sanford Barnes, donated to the Naval History Society by his son, James Barnes, in 1915 and included in the New-York Historical Society's library's collections in 1925. These volumes are now cataloged under the XN call number. Materials were added to subsequently, by donation or purchase, with monies from the Naval History Fund.
  Loose materials originally inserted in the Library Accession Book, including a 1933 rare book auction catalog, details of the Meade donation (see Series 30, Series 31), and a list of portraits of John Paul Jones, have been arranged here chronologically in separate folders.
  - Notebook: "Desirable Books on Naval History", 1907 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Booksellers' advertisements (1 of 2), 1917-1938 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Bookseller's advertisements (2 of 2), 1917-1938 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, 1919-1930 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Materials separated from Library Accession Book: Miscellaneous notes and printed items, 1920-1940, undated (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on naval literature, 1921-1943 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, 1931 (1 of 2) (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, 1931 (1 of 2) (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, 1932 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Materials separated from Library Accession Book: Rare Americana auction catalog, Charles Heartman, 1933 January 28 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, 1933-1935 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Materials separated from Library Accession Book: listing "Books and manuscripts from the library of Richard Worsam Meade (4th)", 1934 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Meade donation bookplates, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, 1936-1937 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Booksellers' catalog, 1938-1943 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Materials separated from Library Accession Book: "Prints, Portraits and Memo. of John Paul Jones", Undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Booksellers' catalogs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of library collection installation, Undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Research materials; library catalog cards, undated (Box 28)
  - Research materials; "Ships of US Navy Built in NY", "US Navy Officers Born in NY State", Lloyd family of Long Island, miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 29)
  - Library Accession Book, 1916-1941 (Volume 3)
- Series V: Financial records (1910-1936)
  The Society's financial records include receipts, vouchers (deposit slips and receipted bills for office expenses and rent), returned checks, checkbooks, account books, information on holdings of securities, and deposits of membership payments. The checkbook stubs document the Society's expenses, while the account books include membership information such as annual dues paid and lists of members.
  The folder titles are taken from the original envelope titles and are not consistent.
  - Bank book, 1910 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Checkbooks, 1910-1912, 1926 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1920 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1921 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1922 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1923 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1924 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1925 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Bank statements and returned checks, 1926 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Vouchers, 1909-1910 Nov 1 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Vouchers and receipts, 1912 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Vouchers and receipts, 1912, 1921 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Vouchers and receipts, 1913 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Vouchers and receipts, 1922 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - [Bills for office expenses: rent, telephone], 1922 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Vouchers and receipts, 1924-1925 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1925 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Member donations to the Building Fund, 1910-1925 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Leases for office in Aeolian Hall, 1915-1925 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Rent receipts for Aeolian Hall office, 1916, 1919-1925 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Sale of Barnes's securities, 1921 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Securities holdings, 1921 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Checkbook, 1912-1916 (Volume 4)
  - Checkbook, 1916-1917 (Volume 5)
  - Checkbook, 1917-1918 (Volume 6)
  - Checkbook, 1918-1919 (Volume 7)
  - Checkbook, 1919-1921 (Volume 8)
  - Checkbook, 1921-1923 (Volume 9)
  - Checkbook, 1923-1925 (Volume 10)
  - Account Book, 1909-1912,1932-1936 (Volume 11)
  - Account Book, 1909-1916 (Volume 12)
  - Account Book, 1916-1924 (Volume 13)
  - Account Book, 1920-1924 (Volume 14)
  - Account Book, 1924-1926 (Volume 15)
- Series VI: Manuscript collections and Naval History Society publication records (1909-1939)
  The Naval History Society's publications were based on its manuscript collections, which it acquired by donation and by purchase, beginning with the collections of John Sanford Barnes. The records consist of acquisitions lists, information on donations received, lists of volumes published by the Society, and a bound volume of Naval Records. Its inclusion here is unexplained. Additional information about manuscript acquisitions is included in the Library Accession Book in Subseries IV. Library records.
  Chronology of Naval History Society Publications
  1911: First volume of Naval History Society publications issued to the subscribers: "Logs of the Serapis, Alliance, Ariel Under the Command of John Paul Jones, 1778-1780," edited by John S. Barnes, and printed by DeVinne Press, New York (see Series 49).
  1912: Second volume: "Fanning's narrative: being the memoirs of Nathaniel Fanning, an officer of the revolutionary navy, 1778-1783," edited and annotated by John S. Barnes, and printed by DeVinne Press, New York.
  1913: Third volume: "The Dispatches of Molyneux Shuldham, Vice-Admiral of the Blue and Commander in Chief of his Britannic Majesty's Ships in North America, Jan-July 1776," edited by Robert W. Neeser and printed by DeVinne Press, New York (see Series 22).
  1914: Fourth and fifth volumes: "The Out-Letters of the continental Marine Committee and Board of Admiralty, 1776-1780," Vols I and II, edited by Dr. Charles Oscar Paulin and printed by DeVinne Press, New York (see Series 22).
  1915: Sixth volume: "Letters and Papers relating to the Cruises of Gustavus Conyngham, a captain of the Continental Navy, 1777-1779," edited by Robert W. Neeser and printed by DeVinne Press, New York (see Series 10).
  1915: "Catalogue of the books, manuscripts and prints and other memorabilia in the John S. Barnes Memorial Library of the Naval History Society".
  1916: Seventh volume: "The Despatches of Thomas Graves, R.N., 1781," edited by Rear Admiral French E. Chadwick, U.S.N. and printed by DeVinne Press, New York.
  1917: Eighth volume: "The Papers of Francis Gregory Dallas, U.S. Navy. Correspondence and Journal, 1837-1859," edited by Gardner W. Allen and printed by DeVinne Press, New York (see Series 12).
  1918: Because of the war and accompanying paper shortages, no publications are issued for the year.
  1920: Ninth and tenth volumes: "The Fox Papers, being the confidential correspondence of Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy during the Civil War," Vols. I and II, edited by Colonel Robert M. Thompson and Rear Admiral Richard Wainwright and printed by DeVinne Press, New York (see Series 17).
  1922: Print based on Garneray's "USS Constitution captures HMS Guerriere" is sent to members.
  1931: Eleventh volume: "Rope yarns from the old navy," by Rear Admiral Caspar F. Goodrich, published by J.J. Little & Ives Co. (see Series 21).
  1932: Twelfth and thirteenth volumes: "Letter-books and order-book of George, lord Rodney, admiral of the White squadron, 1780-1782." New York, printed for the New York Historical Society, 1932, edited by librarian Dorothy Barck (see Series 39).
  1932: H.A.S. Dearborn's "Life of William Bainbridge Esq. of the United States Navy," edited by James Barnes and published by Princeton University Press, is sent to members as "a token of gratitude" (see Series 1)
  1934: Joseph Gurn's "Commodore John Barry: Father of the American Navy" is distributed to members as volume 14 in lieu of a Society publication, "because the Society's large collection of Barry manuscripts was largely used in its compilation" (see Series 5).
  1936: Fifteenth, sixteenth, and seventeenth volumes: "Naval documents related to the quasi-war between the United States and France. Naval operations ... February 1797-December 1801," published under direction of the Honorable Claude A. Swanson, Secretary of the Navy. Prepared by the Office of Naval Records and Library, Navy Department, under the supervision of Captain Dudley W. Knox, U.S. Navy (ret.)
  All materials were originally in mixed folders and boxes; they are arranged chronologically.
  - "War of 1812: The original drawings": list and correspondence from bookseller A.S.M. Rosenbach, 1909 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Library of Congress catalog cards for Naval History Society publications, 1912-1920 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - List of publications of the Naval History Society, 1914-1936 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Clippings; lists of manuscript donations, 1924, undated (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Documentation of provenance of various manuscript and object collections, 1932-1936, undated (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Naval History Society publications: booksellers' catalog listings, 1935-1938 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Catalogs, reprints, 1936-1942, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - List of Naval History Society publications, 1937, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Items from Barnes and Goodrich collections, 1938-1939, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - "Labels for Special Naval Manuscripts Exhibition in Naval History Gallery, March-April-May, 1939" (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition labels for naval medals, Undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Index to Naval War Records, 1861-1865 (Volume 16)
- Series VII: Ephemera (1851-1947)
  The subseries consists of invitations, programs, clippings, visual and printed materials, postage stamps, and a scrapbook on naval topics. The provenance of these materials is unclear; some of the earlier items may have come from the collections of John Sanford Barnes (see Series 3). Materials separated from named collections include an 1851 invitation to Lieutenant Duer (see Series 14), various undated photographs labeled as from Admiral McCauley (see Series 21), and a 1906 invitation to a Naval Ball honoring Rear Admiral Goodrich (see Series 29).
  - Ephemera separated from named collections: Duer, Goodrich, McCauley, 1851, 1906, undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Invitations and programs, 1883-1936 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Various ephemera and clippings, 1911, 1917, 1918, undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Naval-themed postage stamps, 1936, 1945, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Bookplates and calling cards, Undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Reproduced images, Undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook of clippings on naval topics, 1913-1916 (Volume 17)